– Hello. Okay, great. My name is Daniel
Hardman. I am a CEO of a company that is
in the telecom space. I've been working in
identity for many years. And I got an
almost impossible assignment from
Christopher and crew, which is to try to
summarize the state of the identity
landscape in 10 minutes. And that's almost
impossible because there's so much that's
happening and that has been happening. So,
you know, being a progressive thinker
here, I said, I'll ask AI to help me find
a list of things that are going on in the
space. Now, I knew that this was going to
generate massive amounts of stuff. So, I
said, just find 40 headlines that have
been in the news recently in English about
things that are going on in identity that
have been widely reported. So this is what
it came up with and this is of course an
AI summary but the point of this is not
the specific headlines. The main point of
it is how many of them there are and how
hard it was even for the AI to pick from
all the different things that are going on
in the space. And as I was watching this
list come in from AI what was going
through my head that is that Billy Joel
song, We Didn't Start the Fire. You know
what I'm talking about? There's just so
much that's happening and it's virtually
impossible or overwhelming to keep track
of it all. So to summarize in 10 minutes
is very hard, but what I'm going to do is
I'm going to try to explain how it looks
to me as a practitioner in the space at a
high level. I'm going to make some
generalizations. These generalizations are
partly subjective, perspective, but I
think they're a useful mental model for
people to understand if you're not
thinking about identity all the time and
you want to kind of wrap your brain around
it. So, my generalizations basically say
that there have been three waves of
innovation in identity and I would start
the really interesting and this is digital
identity by the way. I would start these
waves going back to something like maybe
the Diffie-Hellman. Diffie-Hellman was a
cryptographic technique that was invented
in 1976. You could possibly go back to
email which was a little bit earlier than
Diffie-Hellman. But anyway, and then I
would say that there's these three bands
of or waves of innovation and they have
characteristics that are common or
commonalities in the way they think about
things. These aren't exactly
perfectly aligned technologies in each of
these bands, but they have these common
characteristics. So I'm not sure what
happened there. Maybe my laptop is still
alive. I'm going to keep talking. Maybe we
can get it to come back up. Okay. So the
first band here, central or federated
governance, it was an assumption that when
you built identity systems initially there
was going to be some central body that did
it for you. And it was an assumption that
you were going to use this brand new cool
thing called Diffie-Hellman and this brand
new cool thing called asymmetric
cryptography and all that kind of good
stuff. And that you were going to use keys
and certificates. That was kind of the new
kid on the block that was cool at the
beginning. And a lot of innovation has
happened since then that kind of keeps
those key assumptions. solutions. And by
the way, when I represent these three
bands here, I'm not saying that there's
bad and okay and better so much as I'm
saying it's kind of like a classic car
that had a carburetor and then a car that
has a fuel injector and a computer and
then an electric car or something. These
are waves of technology. There are reasons
though why we learn from our experience.
And so there is thinking in these later
bands that looks back at what was done in
the earlier bands and says there might be
a better way to do this and there's
advantages to tweaking our mental model.
So the second band of identity innovation
I would kind of track back HIPA is kind of
an outlier in the fact that it came about
pretty early and by the way HIPA has Utah
roots. I didn't know that until yesterday
I was talking to somebody. But anyway,
really kind of when blockchain started
impinging on people's consciousness, there
were a number of things that people said,
oh, wait a minute. That means there's a
different way that we could do this. Oh,
there's a different way we could do that.
And there were some dominoes that fell and
it brought about this yellow band of
thinking. And the thing that's different
mainly between the red and the yellow is
that we're using generation two techniques
where we're not identifying people by
keys. Now we're identifying people by
identifiers. And we're using probably
upgraded cryptography like elliptic curve
and so forth. And there's a lot of
blockchain, although it's not all
blockchain oriented in the yellow band.
But there's a lot of the notion of
wallets, digital wallets was a big deal.
And then there are a lot of dissonance
around privacy issues as this yellow band
kind of came about. out. The third wave of
thinking here, this green band is typified
in my mind by a much more sophisticated
and nuanced view about the governance that
has to be in place. And that doesn't mean
that people that are making yellow banded
stuff or red banded stuff are ignorant
about governance by any means. But it's
kind of like playing a symphony. There's a
lot of different instruments and I think
in the green band the full range of
instruments is now much more apparent. And
big emphasis on auditability of what's
going on in a system and a big emphasis on
recoverability. If something goes wrong
and you assume in the green band that
things will go wrong. So the question
becomes what do you do when things go
wrong? wrong, not how do you prevent
things from going wrong, which is an
unrealistic question in some ways. And
there's different cryptographic
primitives. There's identifiers, yes, but
they're upgraded to autonomic identifiers
which have certain desirable properties,
so forth. And an emphasis on look post
-quantum is going to be a reality soon.
Are we ready for it? It would be really
foolish to build an identity system that's
not ready for post-quantum at this point
when NIST has already announced post
-quantum standards.
Okay, so enough on that slide. I can't
spend that much time because there's just
like I said 10 minutes is nearly
impossible here. What I see in the market
is that there's major tensions. There's
things that are pulling solutions to the
yellow and the red band. hands and you can
see what I've said roughly kind of argues
for yellow and red solutions today. And
then there's things that pull people
towards the green direction when they're
designing solutions.
Enough said on that. I could go into this
for hours, but let me just talk about the
two biggest forces that I see in the
market today. I just returned from living
in Europe for several years. So I've lived
personally through the EUDI initiative a
little bit and what's going on there. And
the EUDI initiative has enormous, enormous
momentum. It's a juggernaut in Europe. But
it doesn't, it's not without its
challenges. many different countries have
built systems and they kind of don't all
get along, but they're trying really hard.
And the state of play in the United States
is a little bit different. You have state
level initiatives, which is why this
conference makes so much sense. States are
making the decisions, not a central
government. There are things that are
being built with generation one solutions
or generation two solutions in the United
States. Absolutely. SEDI is an example of
a generation three solution and there's
reasons why I think that's really
exciting. The strategic trends that I'm
aware of, I'm not going to say them all,
but you can read them there. I'll just say
that the thing I would bet on, bet my
bottom dollar on, is that last bullet.
Security pressures are going to grow and
legal pressures are going to grow. I
guarantee that's going to be true. If
nothing else that I can forecast, that
one's for sure. Remember what that might
imply about what kinds of solutions are
wise. I'd like to end with a thought here
and that is we sometimes hear solutions
described in terms of formats. So, you're
going to hear today about ISO mobile
driver's licenses and you're going to hear
about W3C verifiable credentials and so
forth. I think that's the wrong way to
think about decisions. Up here you have
two pictures of the same person and one of
them is the lossless view that you get off
of a digital camera when you take an image
and the other one is a JPEG. Now, are
JPEGs bad? No. We use them all the time
and they're very useful. But if you're a
professional graphic artist, you would
never want to deal in JPEGs as inputs to
your graphic projects. So they have
different uses. And I'd like to suggest
that permanent evidence needs to be
lossless evidence. And there are a number
of dimensions to losslessness. There's
time-related dimensions like how long does
this evidence persist. There's governance
-related dimensions to evidence. There's
post-quantum cryptography related
dimensions to evidence and losslessness.
There's all kinds of stuff. So I'd like to
just suggest that as you run into
conversations about this, don't make it a
debate about formats. Make it a debate
about how to solve problems and you'll
find that the format questions fall out.
Thank you.